audio notes on some accept from angry
tyrannical book of laws
translated by venerable aria monster
because endowed with four things a
foolish unlearn bad man keeps himself
wounded injured and blameworthy subject
to criticism by the wise he accumulates
much demerit would fall without having
found out without having scrutinized
he speaks praise of one who should not
be praised without having found out
without having scrutinized he speaks
this praise of one who should be praised
without having found out without having
scrutinized he manifests clarity in the
area which should not be clarified
without having found out without having
scrutinized he manifests no clarity in
an area which should be clarified the
these bhiku are the four things endowed
with which foolish unlearned bad man
keeps himself wounded injured and and is
blameworthy and subject to criticism by
the wise he accumulates much demerit
this is pretty self-explanatory however
it's important to take this seriously
basically as in the the common view is
among those who try to practice the
Dhamma but if not necessarily develop the right
but if not necessarily develop the right
view yet the common view is well as long
as I'm trying my best I'm not doing any
harm but that's that's exactly what this
with the point that there were some
other suitors in the beginning of on
katrinka I remember correctly but it
doesn't matter whether you think they
were cheer praising what you're sort of
singling out his word in dumb and so on
it doesn't matter whether you you you
genuinely believe it or not what matters
is whether that thing actually is so or
not whether it is according to the
whether it is according to the practice
so that's why it says here that a
foolish man hasn't scrutinized hasn't
scrutinized and he did not find out for
himself which means it's it's a it's a
50-50 chance that whatever that man is
praising and firing praiseworthy he
might actually be blameworthy from the
ultimate obviously point of view of the
Dhamma in the same sense but what that man
in the same sense but what that man
might might be thinking it's important
for the person it's important for the
clarity he might not be so before that
man starts praising and starts pushing
for it and starts sort of instructing
others even he should know it for
himself whether it is according to the
Dhamma in which case yeah it is
praiseworthy whether it isn't often what
people might be judging is a blame word
it actually isn't there are numerous
examples in the suitors there's even the
one were what was in relation to the
monks but obviously works for anyone or
day no no no day and we said oh here is
a man who is very agreeable to live with
very polite with others very softly
spoken lovely person and everybody loves
him but he's completely full of wrong
views another petitioner has no
distinction has no knowledge has no
attainment and so everybody will praise
him obviously because he's such a nice
person and nobody will we'll find him
blameworthy due to the fact that he's
not even a soda bunny
yeah the Buddha says he should be blamed
would he should be blamed because
anybody can learn nice soft politeness
and words and son and again it's not
either/or as well so a person can be
both but in case that it isn't what you
should look for is the views the way
they live the way they teach not the way
the society or the group would deem
appropriate or not
then the Buddha goes on saying the
another type of man is it's hard to live
with and they can't what people don't
like them but they're sold upon us or
our hands fully enlightened but people
blame them because obviously they have
no criteria for what is blame word and
that's what this earth talks about in
terms of the one who does do that who is
aware that he doesn't fundamentally has
a great to have a criteria but then goes
ahead praising or blaming he accumulates
much demerit carries on here because
endowed with four things of wise learned
good man keeps himself unwanted and
injured and his blameless and not
subject to criticism by the wise and he
accumulates much merit which for having
found out having scrutinize he speaks
praise of one who should be praised
having found out having scrutinized he
speaks this praise of one who should not
be praised having oh yeah and that
there's another thing he speaks this
praise because often people think oh I
must not criticize ya you should not
criticize from your own vanity point of
view or conceit but if you're talking
about a perspective of practice in this
case there's clearly right and wrong if
you don't point out wrong well that's
your fault he speaks this praise of one
who should not be praised so when I say
you point out wrong you don't gonna like
ranting on no bells and and in and so on
but if asked if if the context is there
the Buddha himself would list all the
wrong ways people would be practicing at
the same time wrong things they're doing
misguided things they're doing because
often by investigating why the wrong
thing is wrong you get to understand
what's right so having found out having
scrutinized he manifests no clarity in
an area which should not be clarified
having found on having scrutinize he
manifest clarity in an area which should
be clarified that's pretty much not
knowing what's important
not knowing unimportant from important
and then regarding unimportant things is
that which is really investigated put
loads of effort in and it often happens
these days where people confuse practice
with sort of learning of a behavior like
just refining your politeness and
behavior is confused for the practice of
Dhamma and then loads of effort goes
into it and as I said it's not either/or
you can do both but if you do that
thinking that's what practice of Dhamma
is well then you won't be finding our
practice of dummies because you already
think you found it so it will lead to
much of your demerit whoever praises the
blame would or police's he should be
criticized he selects with his mouth a
misdeed with he with this misdeed he
does not experience happiness that
concludes that except on the first page
again we will include the PDF from which
I'm reading this in the link in the
description video so people can download
it for themselves okay there's a change
the topic now so because if while
walking a thought of sense desire or a
thought of ill-will or a thought of
harming arises for a bhikkhu and if that
big who tolerates it does not abandon it
does not remove it does not get rid of
it does not bring into non-existence
then because while walking that big we
said to have become thus not ardent
unafraid of wrongdoing constantly
continuously lazy lacking energy so the
important distinction distinction here
is to to notice that whether it's a
thought of sense desire in a will of
harming they arise on their own it says
if a thought arises for a bit you may
not seem like a big deal but it's often
very crucial because people people tend
to overreach when people when people
sort of try to practice this attitude of
not tolerating not welcoming and
literally they more like end up acting
out of a version of trying to get rid of
the unpleasant feeling caused by that
which they don't want and they're just
another way of revolving around your own
craving so you want to recognize the extent of
so you want to recognize the extent of
the recent phenomena and when I say
extent I mean how far it has a reason on
its own and then you don't add anything
to it oh you're trying to take away from
it as in you you know how far you should
go and then not cross that mark so it
says here if a thought arises a
real-world sense these are harming if it
arises for a big goal so that in itself
it's not a problem arising of a thought
it's what mine does thoughts arise for
the mind but then the problem becomes if
that big who starts tolerating it if he
doesn't then make the effort to abandon
he doesn't remove it in a sense of the
like say say a thought of sensual desire
arisen and he welcomed it he
automatically just welcomed it and then
he doesn't make an effort to abandon
that welcoming he doesn't make any
effort to stop tolerating it that's
where the problem is so in that sense if
a person starts discerning this the
threshold after which their effort
should be applied or before depending
how you look at it but if they if they
if they are able to discern the extent
of the phenomenon reason on its own and
then see what what they are responsible
for in it because you're not responsible
for its arising you're responsible for
is for its maintenance through
tolerating welcoming indulging it being
careless delighting in it but once
that's discerned then you realize you
cannot unintentionally slip away from
your mindfulness you slip away from the
mindfulness when you intentionally
choose to notice we intentionally choose
to ignore their reason thought and
something that you should not be
welcoming and delighting in and then as
a result of it you welcome it and you
delighted that's how mindfulness is lost not
that's how mindfulness is lost not
because you stopped watching a moment
after a moment or you slipped no it's by
giving in to unwholesome even on the
mental level and it's important to know
what the extent of that phenomena is as
in the
extent of its independence because
otherwise you'll be denying everything
and nothing you'll be trying to fix
everything even when you don't even know
whether it's a problem or not
and that makes a problem so then it goes
on saying if while standing I thought of
census our deal will or harming arises
for a bit go and that big who tolerates
it does not abandon it yeah if while
sitting down if while lying if while
walking so doesn't matter the way your
body is disposed if thoughts have a
reason on their own there you have to be
vigilant not in regards to the content
of your thoughts but in regard to its
nature their nature are those thoughts
by taking in the domain of sensuality
are those thoughts by taking in the
domain of ill-will are those thoughts
were taking in the domain of harming if
so you don't welcome it you let it into
your day because it has a reason on its
own but because of that if you don't
interfere it will cease on its own and
that's the the great inside of the
sotapanna whatever has the nature of
arising because of that it will have to
cease but it's its people's confusion
and ignorance in regards to the
manifestation of phenomena did they get
up get all caught up and in the impound
by those phenomena and affected so if
because while sitting down a thought of
sense desires all available or thought
of harm your eyes for a bhikkhu and if
that bhiku does not tolerate it he
abandons it he brings it to
non-existence then it said that he has
become ardent afraid of wrongdoing
constantly continuously dissolved in
energetic resolute so again he resolved
an energetic is a description of
somebody who is recognized where the
work is and the work is not in denying
your thoughts not in denying mind from
thinking not in denying thoughts from
manifesting but in denying your delight
in it you're careless welcoming your
careless non abandoning your careless
indolence so you just remove that bit
and you become resolved in energetic you
don't have to be dealing with everything
all the time because if things are not
sensual not based on your will not based on
not based on your will not based on
anger and harm there is no problem you
will automatically be mindful because
you're not engaging in anything
unwholesome so let's that was by the way
that wasn't good to the 411 so now let's
have a look at next except because
they're these four strivings which for
striving by restraint striving by
abandoning striving by developing
striving by guarding and which because
is driving by restraining here because
apical having seen a site where the eye
is not one who grasp the science he's
another one who grasped the attributes
of that site since by dwelling with the
eye faculty unrestrained even evil
unwholesome phenomena of covetousness
and grief would invade him he practices
for restraint of it he casts the eye
faculty here and this girl's restraining
the eye faculty
having heard a sound with the having
smell the smell with the nose having
taste the taste with the tongue I
haven't touched a touch with the body
having imagining an image with the mind
he's not the one who grasped the sound
he's not the one who grasped the
attributes since by dwelling with the
mind faculty unrestrained since we're
dwelling with the mind faculty
understand even on wholesome phenomenon
covetous in grief could invade him so
this is the way of this is pretty much
how the wisdom begins you recognize
things before they come your way when
they affect you so you want to start
foreseeing it so you you foresee that so
you're not necessarily guarding yourself
from from from this particular side of
that particular side although that's how
it's gonna end up being because you're
guarding yourself from the nature of
unguarded eye having the experience of
our God that I can then result in those
sights and sounds so you don't want to
be just avoiding things that aren't
wholesome to look at smell taste hear
and touch and think about you actually
want to see that the attitude of the
mind that precedes engaging with those
type of things
so that's what you want to start
restraining because then all you need to
do is keep an eye on your eye so to
speak and you don't that nothing can
enter it but no amount of avoiding
unwholesome things if you don't keep an
eye on on your eye you can only avoid
those things only so fast
sooner or later something's gonna slip
through and your mind will be affected
by covetousness in grief then the next
one is a little bit cause is striving by
abandoning here because a bhikkhu does
not tolerate and the reason thought of
sense desire he abandons it he removes
it this is what we just spoke about he
brings it to non-existence so he stops
fueling it so it was subside he does not
tolerate thought of ill-will and there's
no tolerate evil unwholesome phenomena
whenever they arise so whenever they
arise he stopped tolerating their
arising he's
welcoming it that's what means you get
rid of it you can't prevent it from
arising but you can prevent it from
being fueled further and then he was
stopped rising there is no fuel for it
there will be no ground for its
manifestation then which pig was driving
by developing here because a big who
developed the awakening factor of
mindfulness which is dependent on
seclusion dependent on this passion
depending on cessation resulting in
relinquishment he developed the
awakening factor of discrimination of
phenomena done which he delivers the
awakening factor of energy the awakening
factor of joy the awakening factor of
tranquillity he developed the awakening
factor of composure developed the
awakening factor of equanimity or
indifference which is dependent
seclusion dependent in this passion
dependent cessation is out in delinquent
that is called striving by developing
striving by guarding ok yeah this is
interesting so in which because is driving by
so in which because is driving by
guarding here because big who guards the
arisen helpful sign of composure which
is Samadhi in dimittam the perception of
Bones the perception of war
worm-infested corpse the perception of
discolored corpse the perception of
decaying corpse the perception of
bloated corpse pig who is called
striving by God these because are the
four strivings
so this is already on the level of
proper Samadhi the proper peripheral
mindfulness which is exactly what the
sign of composure arises so you can't
attend to the sign of an arisen thing
signs and tokens of a reason thing are
its characteristics its significance
that it's implied in it which is
inherently in the background it's the
context of the thing you are attending
to so you start discerning the context
the sign of composure as then you start
discerning that there is composure of
your mind present
in regard to the general perception of
the nature of bones the nature of
infested corpse the discoloured corpse
so again those are not things that you
have to keep looking at us or actively
thinking about those those perceptions
that that have a reason are relevant
here because if you discern them on that
peripheral level as that which is in
common to your living body say decaying
corpse decaying corpse or a living body
well they all share the same matter the
same body or rather the nature of the
odour of the matter and the body which
means the decaying corpse and the living
body pertain to the same nature so if
your mind is composed on a more
fundamental perception of a decaying
corpse and it's more fundamental is
because that's how things will
inevitably end up so you realize that
the living it's not that the decaying
corpse is absence of life it's that the
living body is is a delayed decaying
corpse so you want to give priority so
you want to give them a priority to that
which brings dispassion non-attachment
and so on so that's why that's how these
perceptions are helpful it's not like
you have to keep thinking about it
bringing forward being over why because
that won't reveal the nature of it you
want to think about it this color corpse
or decaying corpse and then you want to
see discern its nature being relevant
and applicable to you and that's how
your mind is composed upon that
phenomena which is which does not
contain greed infatuation intoxication
with life and so on so then protecting
that type of composure is what's called
the for right striving striving by
guarding and then it finishes in verses
restraining and abandoning developing
and guarding these are the four striving
stalled by the
Cendant of the sun with these baku here
is ardent not with these baku here is
ardent he has reached the destruction of
suffering that's in glitter of 4:14